A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice, Human Rights and Governance, Office Files of Sara Rios FA1443
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice, Human Rights and Governance, Office Files of Sara Rios
1983-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rios, Sara E.
Ford Foundation
Jenkins, Alan
FA1443
10.48 Cubic Feet 25 boxes (8 letter document boxes, 2 half letter document boxes, 15 legal document boxes)
Scope and Contents
The collection contains miscellaneous office files of Sara Rios, former Director of the Human Rights and Governance Unit within the Peace and Social Justice Division at the Ford Foundation. Her office files contain conference files, reports, press materials, correspondence, and publications. Many grant-related materials in the collection between 1997 and 2000 are the files of Alan Jenkins. Jenkins preceded Rios in her role as Program Officer in the Peace and Social Justice Program from 1997-2000. Some correspondence with grantees and potential grantees is also present after 2000, when Jenkins became Deputy Director of Human Rights and International Cooperation at the Ford Foundation and when he was appointed Director of the reorganized Human Rights Program in 2001.
Biographical / Historical
Sara Rios served as Director of the Human Rights and Governance Unit at the Ford Foundation from 2005-2012. Previously, she was the Program Officer for Racial Justice and Minority Rights from 2002-2005.
Rios earned her Juris Doctor degree at the University of Toledo College of Law and was admitted to the Ohio Bar in 1986. From 1998-2002, she served as Director of Litigation at LatinoJustice PRLDEF.
Rios left the Ford Foundation in 2012 to become president of the Ruth Mott Foundation in Flint, Michigan. She passed away from ALS in 2015.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sara Rios' Office Files arrived at the RAC from the Ford Foundation in multiple accessions between 2018 and 2020 (Accessions 2018:038, 2019:147, 2019:190, 2020:025).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series: Program Officer Files. The collection is organized as received from the Ford Foundation.
Ford Foundation; Human rights; Social justice
- Program Officer Files, 1983-2006; 10.48 Cubic Feet
  - The Civil Rights Project, Harvard University, 1998 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Roundtable Convening on Community-Based Leadership, April 23-24, 1998
  - The Latino Civil Rights Crisis, The Civil Rights Project, 1997 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    A Symposium Co-sponsored by The Harvard Civil Rights Project at Harvard University and The Tomas Rivera Policy Institute
  - A Review of the Ford Foundation's Work Related to Hispanics in the United States, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Uruguay Trip, 2003 May 5-10 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    Notebook - October 2002; correspondence (some in Spanish); Affirmative Action Affinity Group, Montevideo, Uruguay; Summary Outline of Brazilian Legal Issues Affecting Racial Discrimination, Shearman and Sterling (March 6, 2002); Memos; Discussion with Afro-Colombian Mayors (April 22, 2003); Overview of US Affirmative Action Programs and Litigation in the Higher Education Context, Robin A. Lenhardt; Afro-Descendants in Brazil and Uruguay; Affirmative Action Affinity Group; Medicine and the Racial Divide, Elizabeth Phimister; Program Officers' Memorandum Draft by Sara Rios; Disarming the Private Attorney General, Pamela Karlan; High School Graduation Rates in the US; Minority Rights Group newsletter
  - US Court of Appeals 9th Circuit, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Two Towns of Jasper - Outreach Proposal, Presented by Two Tone Productions and Working Films, 2002 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Comision Colombiana de Juristas, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - CivilRights.org Press Printouts, 2002 November 6 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Funders' Collaborative Fund for Racial Justice Innovation, 2003 January 6 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Conference for Community and Justice, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Taking America's Pulse II - Executive Summary; Faith Leaders on Intergroup Relations: Perspectives and Challenges; Hate: A Concept Examined; Taking America's Pulse II: NCCJ's 2000 Suevey of Intergroup Relations in the United States; National Conference for Community and Justice proposal to the Ford Foundation
  - Studies 2000: Discovering the Cultural Formations of Asian and Pacific Island Communities, Wildflowers Institute, 2000 July 23-25 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Center for Voting and Democracy, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Budget information; correspondence; New Electoral Systems for a Changing America, A Proposal to the Ford Foundation for General Support Prepared by Rob Richie, Executive Director, Center for Voting and Democracy (March 2002)
  - Hispanic Civil Rights Series, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Arte Publico Press general info; Arte Publico Press, 2001 Complete Catalog; Hispanic Civil Rights Series general info
  - Alan Jenkins Program Officer's Memo, 1998-2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Citizens' Commission for Civil Rights, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Grant No.: 098011622; grant document drafts; press materials; Rights at Risk: Equality at Risk: Equality in an Age of Terrorism (February 12, 2002)
  - Resolutions on Education, 1970-1993: An Education Department Publication, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - NAACP 1997 88th Annual Convention, Pittsburgh, PA - A Hearing: Does Racial Discrimination Exist in the US Military Justice System, Rachelle M. Jackson, RMR, 1997 July 17 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Field Guide to the Global Economy, Sarah Anderson and John Cavanagh with Thea Lee and the Institute for Policy Studies, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Justice for All?: A Report on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgendered Youth in the New York Juvenile Justice System, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Authors: Randi Feinstein, Andrea Greenblatt, Lauren Hass, Sally Kohn, Julianne Rana; An independent report commissioned by the Lesbian and Gay Youth Project of the Urban Justice Center
  - From Poverty to Punishment: How Welfare Reform Punishes the Poor, Applied Research Center, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Local Government Guide to the Internet, Online Resources for Communities, Priscilla Salant and Christy Dearien, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - National Municipal Policy and Resolutions, National League of Cities, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Adopted at the 2001 Congress of Cities, Atlanta, Georgia, December 8, 2001
  - 2002 Staff Directory, State Municipal Leagues, National League of Cities, 2002 April (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 2002 Directory of City Policy Officials and Resource Guide, Reflects November 2001 Elections, National League of Cities (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Internal: International Human Rights Training for Indigenous Peoples, A Review, Analysis, and Inventory of Programs, The Ford Foundation, 2002 May (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - United States Student Association Foundation, Inc., 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - University of California at Berkeley, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - University of California, Los Angeles - Edward E. Telles Book Project, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - University of Memphis - Race and Nation in the Global South, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - University of Southern California - Justice and Journalism, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Southern Echo, 1998-2001 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    civil rights advocacy, education, and outreach on redistricting and minority rights
  - Southern Education Foundation, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Southern Resource Center - "Who Owns the Past?", 1998-2001 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - WGBH, Frontline - Secrets of the SAT, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Wildflowers Institute, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - William C. Velasquez Institute, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Wisdom Works, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - The Working Group - Not In Our Town, 1999-2001 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Southern Regional Council - Will the Circle Be Unbroken, 1998-2001 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Tomás Rivera Policy Institute, 1997-1999 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Pro Bono Institute, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - The Progressive Media Project, 1997-2001 (Box 6, Folder 45, Box 7, Folder 46)
    Also filed as The Progressive, Inc.
  - Rutgers University - Employment Discrimination, 1998-2001 (Box 7, Folder 47-50)
  - Appleseed Electoral Reform Project, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Asian Immigrant Women Advocates, 1996-1999 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Brennan Center - Race, Redistricting, and Census 2000, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Jack Bass - Unlikely Heroes, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Bazelon Center for Mental Health Law, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Center for Community Change, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Center for Public Integrity, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Southern Regional Council/George Esser Documentation, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Globalvision - Florida Voting Rights Documentary, "Counting on Democracy", 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Humanitas, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - The Impact Fund, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Institute for Democracy Studies - Affirmative Action Proposal, 1996-1999 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Interights, The International Centre for the Legal Protection of Human Rights - Implementing European Anti-Discrimination Law, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - KRCB Television 22 - Northern California Wine Industry Documentary, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Kurdish Human Rights Project, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - LLEGÓ, National Latino/a Lesbian and Gay Organization - Grassroots Organizing, Community Mobilization and Proactive and Reactive Media Presence, 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - University of Michigan - Promoting the Defense of Diversity, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - ACLU of Northern California, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - AfroCaribbean and AfroLatinAmerican Women's Network - Strategy of Participation and Impact of Black Women at the World Conference Against Racism, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - America Online, Digital City, Network of Alliances Bridging Race and Ethnicity (NABRE), and Western Justice Center - From Talk to Action: Transforming Dialogues Online Into Local Action Agendas, 1999-2000 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - American Friends Service Committee - Global Voices Project, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - American University - The Race, Ethnicity, and Gender Justice Project in the Americas, circa 2000 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - MTV - Fight for Your Rights: Take a Stand Against Discrimination and Rock the Vote Education Fund, 1996-2001 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - National Association of Latino Elected and Appointed Officials Educational Fund, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium (NAPALC) - Asian American Capacity Building, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium (NAPLAC) is now Asian American Justice Center (AAJC)
  - National Black Lesbian and Gay Leadership Forum, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - National Campaign for Jobs and Income Support, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - National Council for Burned Churches - Anti-Racism Media Project, 1999-2000 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - The National Council for Research on Women - UN World Conference on Racism, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - National Employment Law Project (NELP) - Workfare and Low-Wage Workforce Project, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - National League of Cities Insurance Institute - Reducing Racism, 2000-2001 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - National Newspaper Publishers Association - Strategic Analysis for Gender Equity (SAGE) and World Conference Against Racism (WCAR), 2001 (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - National Newspaper Publishers Association - Funding Proposals for The Black Press Institute and NorthStar News Service, 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - Poverty and Race Research Council, 1998-2001 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Educational Fund (PRLDF) - Capital Campaign, 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - Paul Quinn College - Redistricting, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - Sakhi for South Asian Women - Project Proposal: Breakthrough - Mainstreaming Human Rights, circa 2000 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Seattle Public Defender - Racial Disparity Project, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - Songmasters - The American Road, 2000-2001 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  - South East Asian Research and Action Council, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - University of Southern California - Institute for Justice and Journalism, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - University of Texas, Sheila Walker - Pan-American Africa/Pan-African America: The African Diaspora in the Americas, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - United Nations Department of Public Information - Fellowship Programme for Journalists from Developing Countries to Cover the World Conference Against Racism, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - United Nations Research Institute for Social Development - Racism and Public Policy Conference, South Africa, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - George Washington University - Research on Minority Citizens' Attitudes Toward and Experiences with the Police, 2000-2001 (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - World Association of Community Radio Broadcasters - Voices without Frontiers, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 96)
  - National Video Resources - Viewing Race Outreach Project, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 97)
  - Youth Law Center - Building Blocks for Youth, 1998-2000 (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - Adalah: The Legal Center for Arab Minority Rights in Israel - 1999 Annual Report (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - Action for Grassroots Empowerment and Neighborhood Development Alternatives (AGENDA) - Communications Proposals, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - American Civil Liberties Union Foundation, Inc.- Racial Justice and Voting Rights, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - American Indian Lawyer Training Program, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  - Applied Research Center - Racial Justice Report Card, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 103)
  - Arizona State University - Translating Legal Cultures: Civil Rights Advocacy in Brazil and the United States, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - Black Leadership Forum, 1997-1998 (Box 11, Folder 105)
  - Trustees of Boston University - National Commission on Testing and Public Policy, 1997-1998 (Box 11, Folder 106)
  - Brennan Center for Justice, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - The Regents of the University of California, Berkeley - The Elimination of Affirmative Action in Higher Education: A Policy Study, 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 108-109)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights (Box 12, Folder 110-111)
  - Chicago Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, 1998-2000 (Box 12, Folder 112)
  - Citizens' Commission on Civil Rights, 1994-2000 (Box 12, Folder 113)
  - Civil Rights Forum, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 114)
  - Clark Atlanta University - Southern Center for Studies in Public Policy, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 115)
  - Communications Consortium Media Center, 1998-2000 (Box 13, Folder 116-117)
  - Community Partners (Box 13, Folder 118)
  - Ellis Cose - UN World Conference on Racism and Xenophobia, 1998-2000 (Box 13, Folder 119)
  - DePaul University - Research on Civil Rights and African American Muslims, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 120)
  - Fair Employment Council of Greater Washington, 1998-2000 (Box 13, Folder 121)
  - FairTest - Equity and Excellence in Higher Education Admissions (Box 13, Folder 122-123)
  - Farmers' Legal Action Group, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 124)
  - Gill Foundation, 1999-2000 (Box 14, Folder 125)
  - Northwestern University - Political Atlas of the African Diaspora, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 126)
  - Harvard Law School Civil Rights Project - The Advancement Project, 1996-2001 (Box 14, Folder 127-128)
  - Hunter College - Global Afro Latino and Caribbean Initaitive (GALCI), 2000-2001 (Box 14, Folder 129)
  - Indian Law Resource Center, 1998-2001 (Box 14, Folder 130-131)
  - University of Minnesota Institute for Race and Poverty - Opportunity Mapping Project, 1998-1999 (Box 15, Folder 132)
  - International Human Rights Law Group, 1997-2000 (Box 15, Folder 133-134)
  - InterSurvey, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 135)
  - The Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies, 1997-2000 (Box 15, Folder 136)
  - Leadership Conference Education Fund, Inc., 1997-2000 (Box 15, Folder 137-138)
  - Leadership Education for Asian Pacifics (LEAP), 1994-1999 (Box 15, Folder 139, Box 16, Folder 140)
  - NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, 1995-2000 (Box 16, Folder 141-142)
  - Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, 1997-2001 (Box 16, Folder 143, Box 17, Folder 144-145)
  - NAACP Special Contribution Fund, 1997-2000 (Box 17, Folder 146)
  - National Research Council - Definition and Measurement of Discrimination, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 147)
  - National Korean-American Service and Education Consortium (NAKASEC) - Immigrant Rights/Civil Rights Advocacy Project, 1996-2000 (Box 17, Folder 148)
  - National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium, 1996-2002 (Box 17, Folder 149, Box 18, Folder 150-151)
  - The National Board on Educational Testing and Public Policy, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 152)
  - Northwestern University - Global Mappings: A Political Atlas of the African Diaspora, 1998-1999 (Box 18, Folder 153)
  - Pace University - Social Justice Center, 1997-1999 (Box 18, Folder 154)
  - Native American Rights Fund, 1997-2000 (Box 18, Folder 155-156)
  - New York Foundation for the Arts - Film Two Productions - Black Feminism, 1993-1998 (Box 19, Folder 157)
  - New York Foundation for the Arts - Kavanagh Productions - Yonkers: A House Divided, 1994-1999 (Box 19, Folder 158)
  - Communications Consortium Media Center and Advancement Project - Voting Rights, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 159)
  - National Council of La Raza, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 160)
  - Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, 1997-2001 (Box 19, Folder 161)
  - Tomás Rivera Policy Institute, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 162)
  - American Indian Research and Grants Assessment Project, 2002 (Box 19, Folder 163, Box 20, Folder 164)
  - American Indian Research and Grants Assessment Project - Untitled, 2002; 3.5 inch floppy disk (Box 20)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Asian American Women Report, Civil Rights, Social Justice, and Black America Discussion Paper, and International Human Rights Law Group Combating Racism Together Report, 1983-2001 (Box 20, Folder 165-167)
  - Alan Jenkins, Director of Human Rights, Response Letters A-Z, 2004 (Box 20, Folder 168, Box 21, Folder 169)
  - Foundation Grants for Civil Legal Advocacy: 1997-Present, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 170)
  - International Human Rights Instruments, circa 2000 (Box 21, Folder 171-173, Box 22, Folder 174-176)
  - Monitoring, Protecting, and Promoting Work Rights in the Global Economy: A Report Prepared for the Ford Foundation, 1999 (Box 22, Folder 177)
  - 9/11 Coordinated Communications Initiative, Responding to the War on Terrorism - Hart Research for Fenton Communications/Ford Foundation, 2001 (Box 22, Folder 178)
  - Overview of Brazil Office, Human Rights Program, Prepared by Edward E. Telles, 2000 (Box 23, Folder 179)
  - Human Rights Communications Mailing, 2003 (Box 23, Folder 180)
  - Human Rights Worldwide Pool, Latin America Region, 2006 (Box 23, Folder 181)
  - Mass Media and Reconciliation: A Report to the Advisory Board and Staff, The President's Initiative on Race, Robert Entman, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 182)
  - Race in Another America: Rethinking Skin Color, Segregation and Life Chances in Brazil, Edward Telles, 2002 (Box 23, Folder 183-185)
  - The Reality of Intentional Job Discrimination in Metropolitan America, Alfred W. Blumrosen and Ruth G. Blumrosen, 1999 (Box 23, Folder 186, Box 24, Folder 187)
    Reports from grant to Rutgers University, Grants #980-1160, 11015-0255
  - The Reality of Intentional Job Discrimination in Metropolitan America, Alfred W. Blumrosen and Ruth G. Blumrosen - Final Report, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 188)
  - Race Matters: Expert Briefing for the United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination, Geneva, Switzerland, Coordinated by the U.S. Racial Discrimination Program of the International Human Rights Law Group, 2001 (Box 24, Folder 189)
  - A Revolution of the Mind: Funding Human Rights in the United States: A Report to the Ford Foundation, Dorothy Thomas, 2001 (Box 24, Folder 190)
  - Southern Social Justice Directory, Southern Organizing Cooperative, undated (Box 24, Folder 191)
  - United Nations International Conference on Population and Development 1994 - Website Printouts, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 192-193, Box 25, Folder 194)
  - The Bellagio Consultation on The United Nations Worldwide Conference Against Racism, Racial Discrimination, Xenophobia and Related Intolerance, Gay J. McDougal, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 195)